A Guide to the Edward Wilson James Papers, 1635-1906
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Edward Wilson James Papers 1635-1906
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
38-402
This collection consists of ca. 500 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Bequest of Edward Wilson James, 1906.
Scope and Content
Personal and business papers, land grants, deeds and other papers signed by Virginia governors and others, relating to the history of Lower Norfolk and Princess Anne Counties, Va., and the James Family. Includes the wills of Jacob Hunter, Edward James, Elizabeth James, John James, and William James, vestry book of Lynnhave Parish, and List of tithable and taxable property, 1784.
Names represented include John Strode Barbour, Sir William Berkeley, Baron de Botetourt, Robert Dinwiddie, John Ffloy, Sir William Gooch, Sir john Harvey, Patrick Henry, Thomas Jefferson, Henry Lee, James Madison, John Page, Beverley Randolph, Edmund Randolph, John West, William Wirt, and James Wood.
Contents List
- John West- Proclamation unto Adam Thoro[w]good (Copy of 1860 January 14, Richmond, 1635 June 24 (Box 1)
- Sir John Harvey, Knt. Governor, also Adam Thorogood (Copy of 1860 January 14, Richmond), 1637 September 19 (Box 1)
- Wm. Berkeley and Adam Thorogood (Copy of January 14, Richmond), 1643 June (Box 1)
- Copy of 1882 May 3, Land off, 1682 April 20 (Box 1)
- Edmund Andros (Copy, ca. 1800), 1696 October 9 (Box 1)
- Samuel Boush Case 1700 January (Box 1)
- Francis Nicholson, Gov. General, 1700 December 18 (Box 1)
- Deed 1707 June 17 (Box 1)
- Document 1708 (Box 1)
- C. Eden, Gov. Of Carolina, 1714 November 22 (Box 1)
- M. Bousch-Warrant, 1714 August 2 (Box 1)
- Document 1718 July 17 (Box 1)
- Document-Norfolk Co. 1719 February 29 (Box 1)
- Document 1722 August 10 (Box 1)
- Minute Book of the Vestery of Linhaven Parrish 1724-1882 (Box 1)
- Wm. Gooch, Lieut-Gov. and Commander-in-Chief 1728 June 13 (Box 1)
- Document 1731 March 18 (Box 1)
- Will of John James, 1734 August 14 (Box 1)
- Indenture, 1736 November 29 (Box 1)
- Document, 1741 December 29 (Box 1)
- Indenture, 1742 February 24 (Box 1)
- Petition, 1746 April 19 (Box 1)
- Indenture, 1751 May 21 (Box 1)
- Tho. Holladay to Dr. Chr. Wright 1752 February 12 (Box 1)
- Bill of exchange, 1756 March 9 (Box 1)
- Bill of exchange, 1756 May 25 (Box 1)
- Deed-Robert Dinwiddie to William Flanakin 1756 August 16 (Box 1)
- Bill of exchange, 1758-1759 (Box 1)
- Document, 1762 July 20 (Box 1)
- Receipt 1762 August 24 (Box 1)
- Document 1763 September 21 (Box 1)
- Bill of Exchange 1763 (Box 1)
- Bill of exchange 1764 April 24 (Box 1)
- Agreement 1764 August 2 (Box 1)
- Bill, 1766 December 5 (Box 1)
- Marriage Agreement 1766 December 5 (Box 1)
- Lease, 1767 February 23 (Box 1)
- Bill of exchange, 1767 July 7 (Box 1)
- Indenture, 1767 August 5 (Box 1)
- Document 1767 October 4 (Box 1)
- Bill of exchange 1767 (Box 1)
- Wm. Woodhouse, Sr., Edward James, Cason Moore- Comissioner's Report 1768 February 16 (Box 1)
- Bill of exchange, 1768 (Box 1)
- Baron de Botetourt, Gov. General 1769 December 22 (Box 1)
- Receipt, 1769 (Box 1)
- Bill of exchange 1770 April 6 (Box 1)
- Bill of exchange 1770 May 17 (Box 1)
- Receipt 1770 August 27 (Box 1)
- List of Tithables, 1771 June 10 (Box 1)
- Wm. Woodhouse-Warrent 1771 August 26 (Box 1)
- Bill of exchange 1772 November 22 (Box 1)
- Bill of exchange, 1772 December 4 (Box 1)
- Indenture, 1773 January 14 (Box 1)
- Bill of exchange, 1773 April 24 (Box 1)
- Bill of exchange, 1773 June 16 (Box 1)
- Bill of exchange, 1774 February 23 (Box 1)
- Account 1774 March 27 (Box 1)
- List of Tithables 1775 June 10 (Box 1)
- Patrick Henry, Governor 1777 May 20 (Box 1)
- Patrick Henry, Governor 1777 May 20 (Box 1)
- Deed 1778 September (Box 1)
- Indenture 1778 December 17 (Box 1)
- Receipt 1779 January 11 (Box 1)
- Will, 1779 February 28 (Box 1)
- Poll Certificate 1779 March 9 (Box 1)
- Copy of Will, 1780 January 24 (Box 1)
- Receipt 1782 March 12 (Box 1)
- Notebooks (4) 1782-1931 (Box 1)
- Will 1783 October 15 (Box 1)
- Princess Anne- (Taxable Property) 1784 (Box 1)
- Blackwater Precinct- (Tithable and Taxable Property) 1784 (Box 1)
- Lower Western Shore- (Taxable Property) 1784 (Box 1)
- Little Creek- (Taxable Property) 1784 (Box 2)
- Eastern Branch- (Taxable Property) 1784 (Box 2)
- Eastern Shore- (Taxable Property) 1784 (Box 1)
- Lower Eastern Shore- (Taxable Property), 1784 (Box 2)
- Upper Precinct of the Western Shore- (Tithable and Taxable Property), 1784 (Box 2)
- Return of Overseers of the poor for the Eastern Branch Precinct, 1786 March 29 (Box 2)
- Will- William Jamessen 1786 September 22 (Box 2)
- A list of persons presented by the Grand Jury and sent to the Attorney General, 1786 November 9 (Box 2)
- Edmund Randolph, Governor 1786 December 5 (Box 2)
- Edmund Randolph, Governor, 1787 February 10 (Box 2)
- Judgement declared on case against John Guy, 1787 March (Box 2)
- Receipt, 1787 November (Box 2)
- Marriage Bond, 1787 December 16 (Box 2)
- Marriage Bond 1787 December 24 (Box 2)
- List of Tithables, 1788 (Box 2)
- Summons, 1789 March 2 (Box 2)
- Document, 1789 March 19 (Box 2)
- Copy of Elizabeth James Will 1789 December 8 (Box 2)
- Document 1789 (Box 2)
- Document, [1789] (Box 2)
- Beverley Randolph, Land Grant, 1790 May 17 (Box 2)
- Receipt, 1791 (Box 2)
- Receipt, 1792 July 22 (Box 2)
- Chancery Suit, James vs. Brock 1792-1798 (Box 2)
- Attachment, 1793 August 19 (Box 2)
- Suit in Chancery between Charles Brock, et al. & John James, et al., 1794 May 8 (Box 2)
- Governor Henry Lee, Comission to Jonathan Woodhouse, 1794 July 16 (Box 2)
- Document, 1794 July 19 (Box 2)
- Appointment of Overseers of the Poor, Little Creek Precinct, 1794 July (Box 2)
- Deposition (Elizabeth Attwood), 1794 August 5 (Box 2)
- Document, 1794 (Box 2)
- Governor James Wood, Commission to Tully Moseley, 1794 (Box 2)
- Moseley vs. Moseley, 1795 (Box 2)
- Marriage Bond, 1796 April 7 (Box 2)
- Moseley vs. Moseley, 1796 May 24 (Box 2)
- Tully Moseley vs Josiah Hunter, 1796 June (Box 2)
- Document, 1796 June (Box 2)
- Bill of Complaint, 1796 (Box 2)
- Deposition- Charles Henry and Pembroke James, 1797 May 8 (Box 2)
- Brock vs. James, 1797 June 6 (Box 2)
- James Wood, Governor, 1797 July 25 (Box 2)
- Court Decision 1797 (Box 2)
- Wm. Brock vs. John James, 1797 (Box 2)
- Indenture, 1799 February 25 (Box 2)
- Indenture, 1799 February 25 (Box 2)
- Bond, 1802 December 6 (Box 2)
- Governor John Page- Comission, 1804 April 28 (Box 2)
- William Wert's opinion on George Gasking's will, 1805 February 21 (Box 2)
- Thomas Jefferson to Edward S. Hall, 1807 July 1 (Box 2)
- Bill and Receipt, 1807 October 13 (Box 2)
- Receipt, 1812 March 3 (Box 2)
- Bill, 1813 March 23 (Box 2)
- Governor J. S. Barbour, 1813 April 1 (Box 2)
- Governor J. S. Barbour, 1813 May 19 (Box 2)
- Copy of Edward James' Will, 1814 October 6 (Box 2)
- Bill of Lading, 1814 December 26 (Box 2)
- Indenture, 1820 May 5 (Box 2)
- Land Grant, 1826 April 21 (Box 2)
- Bill of Sale (slave), 1829 September 9 (Box 2)
- Bill of Lading, 1829 October 3 (Box 2)
- Poem 183? (Box 2)
- Division of the Negroes of James Henley, 1832 December 20 (Box 2)
- Governor John Floyd, 1833 April 3 (Box 2)
- John James to John Cornick, Jr., 1835 February 22 (Box 2)
- John James to Jane Shepherd, 1835 April 5 (Box 2)
- Receipt, 1835 October 17 (Box 2)
- Insurance Policy and Receipt, 1835 December 29 (Box 2)
- Certification of Death, 1839 January, 30 (Box 2)
- Receipt, 1844 April 13 (Box 2)
- Invitations, announcements, ca. 1850-1906 (Box 2)
- Columbia James- Autograph Album, 1856-1858 (Box 2)
- Receipt, 1875 (Box 3)
- Receipt, 1876 December 5 (Box 3)
- James Cormick to E. W. James, 1882 April 21 (Box 3)
- J. M. Brockenbrough to E. W. James, 1882 July 12 (Box 3)
- Jon Hunter to Edward James- (Genealogy), 1883 May and July 23 (Box 3)
- Baptist Church Register, 1883-1884 (Box 3)
- Bank of Commerce, 1885-1900 (Box 3)
- Marine Bank, 1885-1906 (Box 3)
- Micellaneous Norfolk Banks, 1885-1906 (Box 3)
- Norfolk National Bank, 1886-1893 (Box 3)
- Alexander Brown and Sons, 1887-1901 (Box 3)
- Miscellaneous Bills, Receipts, etc., 1890-1896 (Box 3)
- Winston, Colston, and Co., 1892-1905 (Box 3)
- W. H. Lowdermilk and Co., 1895 November 22 (Box 3)
- E. S. James, 1895 (Box 3)
- Norfolk National Bank, 1895 (Box 2)
- Miscellaneous, 1895 and 1905 (Box 3)
- Norfolk National Bank, 1896 (Box 3)
- Miscellaneous Letters, Receipts, etc., 1897 (Box 3)
- Norfolk National Bank, 1897 (Box 4)
- Miscellaneous Letters, Receipts, etc., 1898 (Box 4)
- Miscellaneous Letters, Receipts, etc., 1899 (Box 4)
- Norfolk National Bank, 1899 (Box 4)
- Miscellaneous Letters, Receipts, etc., 1900 (Box 4)
- Norfolk National Bank, 1900 (Box 4)
- Miscellaneous Letters, Receipts, etc. 1901 (Box 4)
- Norfolk National Bank, 1901 (Box 4)
- Miscellaneous Letters, Receipts, Bonds, etc. 1902-1905 (Box 4)
- Norfolk National Bank, 1902 (Box 4)
- Virginia Club to Edward Wilson James, 1903 October 14 (Box 4)
- Norfolk National Bank, 1903 (Box 4)
- Miscellaneous Letters, etc., 1904 (Box 4)
- Norfolk National Bank, 1904 (Box 5)
- Norfolk National Bank, 1905 (Box 5)
- Richard H. Baber and Son to Edward W. James, 1905 (Box 5)
- Wilson, Colston, and Co. to Edward W. James, 1905 (Box 5)
- Diary 1906 (Box 5)
- Miscellaneous Letters, Bills, etc., 1906 (Box 5)
- Norfolk National Bank, 1906 (Box 5)
- Wilson, Colston and Co. to Edward W. James, 1906 (Box 5)
- Miscellaneous 1908-1909 (Box 5)
- Joel Cornick n.d. (Box 5)
- Family Tree n.d. (Box 5)
- Miscellaneous n.d. (Box 5)
- Photographs n.d. (Box 5)
- Unidentified Note, n.d. (Box 5)